thanks to last past for sponsoring a portion of this video.
More from them later.
Ladies and gentlemen,
we build a lot of high performance computers around here,
but today is going to be different.
We scoured the Internet for the slowest brand new components that money can buy,
and we're gonna build it right here right now.
Then for comparison.
We also grab some sort of what I would consider to be budget components but sensible ones to see just how much more performance you can get if you balance your budget,
it's really the packaging for that.
We're gonna get to that bit later,
though.
First,
don't worry,
parts aren't in there already to throw that in joke.
Of course,
my expectations may end up being subverted and our slowest possible computer.
Where's the CPU?
Maybe this will end up being an amazing bang for the buck,
starting with our A M D Athlon 3000 G.
So this poppy right here is a 3.5 gigahertz dual core that's not really impressive for 2020.
And making matters worse,
this is based on Andy's older Zen architecture rather than Zen,
too.
But hey,
for $55 plus could actually includes a cooler,
I guess you know,
it's hard to really.
It's hard to really complain.
Like how is this a few 50 bucks for our mother board?
We've gone with Emma size a 3:20 a.m. A throw.
So this is about as entry level as it gets for an A M for mother board.
You've got just too damn slots,
although that will be enough for us to run dual channel,
assuming that our budget allows it,
which it doesn't because we're building the slowest possible computer has a PC.
I express 60 next Gen three graphics card slot.
We will be installing a graphics card and then you've got onboard video in case you want to use in a pew.
Wow,
most PS two ports tank.
No enviably for us today,
folks.
We're not even using an SSD,
and it feels like this should contribute to it being slow.
But honestly,
with just two cores,
I'm expecting fist into a pretty decent job of cooling.
I feel like I should clarify that the parts that we picked were not necessarily the slowest ones that we could find,
but rather that we limited ourselves to things that are currently in production.
So the slowest brand new and technically modern parts that you can build naturally no slowest possible build would be complete without a single stick of DDR four memory.
The CPU does have a dual channel memory controller,
but I mean,
if we're looking for the bare minimum to fire up the machine and get into Windows four Gigs of Ram,
that's it.
Wow,
you sure can build a computer quickly when there's not much in it.
We're halfway there already.
Between our CPU Mother Board of Ram,
we've spent ah,
$125.
That's less than like a gaming motherboards.
But while you guys might think that I'm impressed by that,
I'm actually kind of worried for the prospects of our slowest possible computer here because CPU ran the mother board on the second hand market pool.
We let me tell you,
I could get some better stuff than that.
You know,
that's what kind of drives me crazy about this entry level hardware as it gets branded.
Really,
what it is is,
in my opinion,
basically e waste because you might say,
Well,
you know,
not everyone wants to put the work in tow,
putting together something second hand,
but it's not even a ton of work.
I mean,
we did that video recently where we took an old Dell OptiPlex basically through a graphics card in it for less than what we're going to spend on this complete brand new machine.
And let me tell you,
a spoiler alert,
this thing is going to run.
What's the opposite of running circles around something?
For our case,
we've got a thermal take H 17 which at the time was priced the same as the deep cool,
not tracks that we had originally chosen.
So $35 point is,
that's about the cheapest you can get unless it's on fire sale for a brand new computer case and then for our power supply.
We've got a Corsair CV 5 50 This is your entry level.
Hey,
I don't want my computer to blow up.
That would be a bad thing kind of power supply if you could get power supplies for $13 or whatever.
But even on a system like this,
I would not recommend plugging them in.
And what's the point of ruining stuff?
Huh?
Four whole screws to put in power split.
Jeepers,
you just need to rehydrate El Sisi stored.
So this is cool.
Kind of like an SSD,
except just with some rubber grommets should just mount your hard drive like that.
So I put in all the screws.
I mean,
there's really not that many of them.
We had a second fan that we intended to install in this puppy,
but I don't think we're gonna be doing that because there's only a single fan header aside from the CPU fan had her on this mother board.
More simplicity,
foam fat installed.
Cable managed is actually pretty nice for a budget case.
Hey.
Wow.
We've got USB three on both our cases and mother board.
I'm sure you guys a little trick.
You could just take all of these little individual pieces and kind of make your own block of connectors.
If you line up just right.
Put it on just like that.
How on dang it.
I stabbed my thumb.
I'm good.
Fine.
24 pin power connector.
Just like that,
you can see instead of an eight pin power connector on this board,
we've got just a four pin.
So we're gonna split apart are eight pin power connector.
Just pop half of it into their This is crazy.
Like if I was actually trying to speed build this,
I think I could do it in under five minutes.
And now for the PS,
tell a resistance our Zo tack G t to 10.
This was a slow graphics card when I was still working at N.
C I X House.
Like eight years ago,
you could still buy them.
I don't even get it.
People who buy a card like this don't care about performance at all,
or they get kind of screwed into it because they don't know that the performance of a $50 card is not half of the performance of $100 card.
I remember talking to Zo Tak about these cards back when I was working in sex.
I was like,
Well,
who the crap is buying these things like,
you know,
best.
Buy's moving through them by the truckload,
and I was like,
Why are their sales people selling these to them?
It's a terrible value point of clarification.
This is 40 U.
S.
Dollars,
not 50 and it's still a bad deal.
Yeah,
for $35 case,
I mean,
I'm liking it crazily enough.
That was it.
By the way,
the key night among you might have noticed that we had an 80 radion fan installed on that graphics card.
That's cause we weren't gonna go out and buy another GT 2 10 just to make this video.
It's one that we already had.
And it's one that the fan failed on a long time ago.
And we just kind of food,
whatever on there,
as long as it runs cool enough time to fire it up.
I miss a little wine.
E g few fans up.
It works.
That took a hot minute to posted it.
Fire up some CS go,
shall we?
And while we wait for the game to load cause it will probably take a minute on the mechanical drive,
we're going to go ahead and pull out our better value gaming PC here.
Our slowest PC came in at a price of just over $300 while our step up model came in at just under 600 which is a pretty substantial increase.
We're spending almost twice as much,
but We're also getting more than twice as much computer.
So we're going all the way up to a rise in 3100 which happens to be based on their Zen to architecture.
That is going to be a big performance boost for gaming.
We managed to double our rant,
going from 4 to 8 gigs,
which also means now it's running in dual channel mode.
We've got a more feature rich mother board and,
ah,
big amount of our budget was spent on this puppy right here.
So we've gone with an Rx 5 70 which is maybe,
you know,
last gen.
At this point,
but still a very,
very respectable budget gaming card.
If we're running a 10 80 p already,
just how much faster and boots Apple launches games is a huge difference for this one.
But of course,
that's what happens when you spend a little bit of extra on an SSD.
And the funny thing about an SSD is that these days it doesn't actually cost that much extra.
If you look for the right deal,
we got our fatted of racing 1 20 gig SSD for 20 bucks.
Eight.
Ex ante releasing eight happen Let's see if that helps a little bit.
Gonna set the settings over here the same.
Oh,
man,
this one defaulted to for Okay.
Ooh,
lordy.
Fly.
That's still loading.
Holy crap!
150.
60 70 200 FPs.
Yep,
This feels this feels pretty good.
All right,
this one's loaded up.
Now let's just make sure the resolutions,
right?
And this kid's is why friends don't let friends by entry level graphics cards.
We are getting 10 FPs.
My ladies and gentlemen's we're charging in.
Though We're charging in,
we might have something.
I got one 10 FPs gaming.
Ladies and gentlemen,
come on.
But friends got it out for me.
So the lesson we're learning here is that spending twice as much can yield Mawr than just twice the performance improvement in this case,
we're looking at about anywhere from 50 next to 20 x,
the performance at the same settings and actually missed another thing that is twice as fast about our higher end system.
It's got USB 3 10 gig instead of five gigs.
So if you really wanted to transfer things quickly over USB,
you could do that.
Oh,
no.
There's a first time set up on this one while we wait for that one to complete set up,
we can go ahead and have a look at what our rocket league performances like.
Yes,
I'm playing with most keyboard.
I'm sorry.
00 I press jump instead of go fast.
Well,
that's a shame.
OK,
so what are we looking?
We're looking at 100 plus FPs with a minimum of 48 the entire time we've been planning here.
And that minimum is honestly mawr important to the gaming experience than that averages rocket leg.
Is this game just not even gonna launch?
Nope.
New plan.
Just for the sake of giving our slowest PC,
it's best possible shot.
We actually ripped the graphics card.
That wasn't letting us launch the game out.
And we're running off of the onboard graphics.
The problem with that is that we're running a single stick of memory because it's a bit of a Miss configured machine and now r a p U graphics has to share memory bend with with the CPU,
which was already half of what it ideally would be.
15 FPs in the menu.
Big goof Linus.
That same settings is the other one.
Oh boy,
You know,
having the game run in slow motion like this is actually kind of nice,
because it's not an online match.
So I think the game is actually running slow.
Finally,
let's go for a good old fashioned center bench drag race.
Are you gonna Are you even trying?
Maybe it didn't register and the 123 go.
I think we've all seen enough,
and I think we've all learned the lesson that we're trying to teach here.
Just because something is brand new off the shelf doesn't mean that it is a viable option for building a system.
And you might say,
Well,
look,
I've only got $50 to spend on a CPU,
and that's fine,
and that's fair.
But your best option at that point is to go back and look for something on the second hand market that is going to give you a better experience than this literally ah,
fraction of the speed of even a value chip like the rise and 3 31 100 really fantastic CPU for the money.
The other thing is graphics.
You know how there's a point of diminishing returns when you go into the very high end stuff.
Well,
there's a point of diminishing returns at the low end as well,
and it's something people don't really think about.
So I would give the same advice there.
In fact,
I don't want you to get discouraged if you've only got $300 to spend on a new computer.
What I want you to do is head down to the comments where some of our sad e bargain hunter viewers are gonna post some grapes back lists that they think they can put together for $300.
Because I guarantee you,
if you head up eBay,
Craigslist in all those kinds of places,
it can be done now for the portion of this video that is sponsored by last past.
Last Pass is the password manager that I use and honestly,
whether it's for personal use or for our corporate use,
I absolutely love it.
The corporate version has all kinds of tools that we can use to manage access to all the different accounts and not just accounts,
but little notes or credit card numbers,
or anything else that our staff needs access to no matter where they are and to do it securely and then for personal use.
Well,
it's great whether I'm using a PC and Android phone or an iPhone.
All I've got to do is enter one password and everything that I need is right at my fingertips.
I'm gonna just check and see if there's any talking points that I'm supposed.
I'm just talking about what I like about last pass right now.
Oh,
yeah,
it's way more secure,
because that way you only have to remember one really strong pass phrase,
and you never have to use duplicate passwords because,
let's face it,
who can remember all the literally hundreds of passwords that you have to have these days last past?
Auto fills your credentials through browser extensions or Absalon Mobile.
And if you go to last past Premium,
they've got advanced features like multi factor authentication options and emergency access.
So go check them out at the link.
In the video description,
I've been using them for years.
I've been super happy,
thanks last past for being awesome and thanks last pass for sponsoring this video.
If you guys enjoy this sort of thing and you're looking to maybe go a little bit deeper than the comments on this video to build a great value gaming rig,
maybe check out our This is a gaming rig where we converted a Dell OptiPlex into a very viable gaming solution.