- Nature.
- [Man] Tasty, oh my God.
Spit that out James.
You, no you didn't.
- I'm a vegetarian mother (beep).
- Valve has given developers
access to the beta
for Steam Cloud Play.
It's unclear exactly what
those new services will
look like for consumers,
but here's what we know.
Steam cloud play can
apparently integrate cloud
streaming services into
your Steam library.
Allowing you to launch
services like GeForce Now
from Steam.
Okay, but why would you
want to do that instead
of just using GeForce Now regularly
or streaming from your own
PC using Steam roleplay?
Well the key difference
here seems to be that
Steam Cloud Play could
involve streaming games,
not from your own PC or in video servers,
but from servers hosted by Valve.
Why do I care?
It also looks like Steam
Cloud Play integration
could help services
like GeForce Now expand
their library of supported
games, that would be nice.
If it's super easy for
publishers to opt in via
Steam platform.
The news comes just as GeForce
Now is actually getting
some triple A games from
Ubisoft back on the platfrom
through the Epic Games store.
But lets be real hey guys, no
one owns those games on EGS.
We all just claim the free games.
Thank you Fortnite.
- [Man] We're not gonna buy
it, if we don't have to.
- Okay, we're gonna talk about Trump
and Twitter now, okay?
But you gotta keep it chill okay.
Lets all just
(breathing in)
This week has seen a tense confrontation
between Twitter and U.S
President Donald Trump,
over a number of his tweets.
It started on Tuesday when Twitter pinned
a fact checking-link to
one of Trump's tweets.
In which he claimed that Mail-In Ballots
will lead to election fraud.
Then on Thursday, Trump
signed an executive order
directing the FCC and FTC to investigate
whether new regulations could be placed
on social media giants
like Twitter and Facebook,
which would effectively
turn them into publishers,
which are liable and could
be sued for the content
they host, instead of merely platforms,
which are not liable for said content.
Currently, Twitter and
Facebook are protected
from liability by section 230 of the
communications indecency act.
There's plants in my mouth.
Which both Trump and Joe
Biden want to overturn.
It's unclear what an order like this would
accomplish for Trump as Twitter
might be more incentivized
to remove sensitive tweets
if they are liable for
hosting certain content.
Which is the very thing that prompted
this whole debacle in the first place!
- [Man] How Ironic!
- I don't get it.
While Twitter is going head
to head with the president,
Mark Zukerburg apparently
wants to just stay out of it.
Robots they don't like drama,
Zuckerburg said in an
interview that Facebook
shouldn't be the arbiter of truth,
even though the platform has been
fact-checking posts about
the American election
and the COVID-19 pandemic.
We'll have to wait and see what the future
of social media looks like
but on the bright side,
at least you can now schedule
tweets on desktop again.
- [Man] Yay!
- Again, not now.
- [Man] Later.
- Yeah in the future.
- [Man] Yeah.
- Now for some lighter news;
HP has unveiled the reverb G2 headset
for desktop powered VR
and it might have just
knocked the index out of
the best VR headset thrown.
It's 599 US with a per eye resolution
of 2160 by 2160 that's a square.
The index panels are just 1440 P.
Its got 9 gigahertz refresh rate,
and a field of view around 114 degrees.
Although, field of view is dependent upon
a number of factors so it's hard
to describe with a single number.
Riley, everybody knows that.
(man laughing)
But Valve apparently isn't scared of the
headset's success, they actually worked
with HP to develop it and you can see that
in the G2's speakers.
Which look like they were
taken right off an index.
Microsoft also helped HP.
They developed the units new windows
mixed reality controllers,
which come with the headset.
The Reverb G2 uses insight to tracking,
no base station is required.
So we'll have to see whether Linux looks
just as silly playing Beat Saber
wearing this thing instead of the index.
Now its time for the quick pit,
brought to you by XSplit Vcam.
All the letters
It can remove, replace, and blur your
screening background
without a green screen.
And it works with any
web cam dammit any one!
So there's no need for
complicated lighting setups.
This isn't film school, its
the internet gosh darn it!
You can customize the
background to anything you want.
And it works with other broadcast tools,
and even messaging apps
like Slack, Hang out, Skype,
and more.
XSplit promises 24/7 support
and life time updates
for as little as 3995
for a life time license
or 995 for a three months.
That's three bucks a month,
that's like a coffee or a flapjack.
You can also use code
LINUSTECHTIPS to get 10% off,
so do that at the link below.
This is like free
in America.
Quick base,
(clearing throat)
What's up.
Hey, did you buy this
$370 dollar USB stick
that promises
to protect you from 5G radiation?
Well I'm sorry, you're an idiot.
No refunds.
You see, it doesn't actually use quantam
hollographic catalyzer technology
for the balance and harmonization
of the harmful effects
of imbalance electrical radiation at all.
It doesn't do anything,
because its a 128 megabyte
USB key with a sticker on
it and you should've known.
Shame on you and your country
which poorly educated you.
And the companies in your country
that let you be in a filter bubble.
Samsung had officially
unveiled a new version
of the Galaxy Book S,
featuring an intel lake-field processor
instead of the qualicom 8CX arm chipset.
If it's good, the first lake-field laptop
could prove arm doesn't have a future
of fit in lights after all.
And intel really needs a wedge right now,
so come on guys, look into your hearts.
I think I saw them last
night outside a bar,
just sitting on the curb
crying into their Budweiser,
And they're not supposed to
bring the glasses outside.
Nvidia has launched Quadro Experience.
A Windows app that fulfills
many of the same functions
for PC's running Quadro graphers cards
as the GeForce Experience
app does for systems
with gaming folk as GeForce cards.
So I guess you're not
gonna download it either.
You just can record 4K
footage, get driver updates,
and optimize games.
But don't forget, you can
run games on a Quadro too.
You are just if you do that
well, you're just spending
a lot more to do that.
Russians, that's how Hilary Clinton says,
the Russians are hacking our emails.
The NSA says a division
of the Russian Military
code named Sandworm, very dune,
has been attacking email servers that run
the extra mail transfer agent.
Its an agent.
Which is used in both private
and Government organizations.
Hopefully, this naming and
shaming will get IT managers
to issue purchase but you know,
the most effective way to kill a sandworm?
- [Man's voice] What is it?
- It's a spoilers
- [Man's voice] I thought
you would know dun!
How do you kill them?
- I can't even respond
to that without spoilers.
- [Man] Jeeez!
- And an app by Yamaha,
called Remote Cheerer,
will let sports fans
who are watching matches
from home to connect to giant speakers
in the stadium so they can
cheer on their teams from a far.
But the players won't
hear your actual voice.
Fans will choose from a preset selection
of cheers, boos, and rhythmic claps.
That's probably for the best.
I host chances this is a recipe
for the biggest zoom bomb ever.
This is so stupid,
- [Man] Come on ref, ooooh!
- Like if there's not a good turn out
then people in the sound board,
are just like turn it up anyway.
- [Man] They are like the cheering is on.
- They really like you.
That's enough of this nonsense,
come back on Monday for more Tech news
and maybe we'll have a building.
Will have to survive on plants!
- [Man] Don't do it James.
How do you feel?
- I'm good, prickly leaf exclusive.
This is actually the best leaf I've eaten.